<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <!-- Details about the document -->
      <fileDesc>
         <!-- Title details. We put respsibility statements in the edition -->
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pipe roll of the English Exchequer for Michaelmas 1304 to Michaelmas 1305 (33
               Edward I)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <!-- Edition details -->
         <editionStmt>
            <!-- For the description (database), use the edition? -->
            <edition>TEI/XML English translation of the Pipe roll of the English Exchequer for
               Michaelmas 1304 to Michaelmas 1305 (33 Edward I)</edition>
            <!-- Responsibility for the edition. -->
            <respStmt xml:id="peter-crooks">
               <name>Peter Crooks</name>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="paul-dryburgh">
               <name>Paul Dryburgh</name>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="lynn-kilgannon">
               <name>Lynn Kilgannon</name>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="elizabeth-biggs">
               <name>Elizabeth Biggs</name>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="mike-jones">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="brendan-smith">
               <name>Brendan Smith</name>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <!-- Details about the extent of the original document. -->
         <extent>A parchment roll of 18 membranes.</extent>
         <!-- Publisher and licence -->
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trinity College Dublin, The University of Dublin</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Dublin</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <!-- License -->
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
            <!-- Contact details -->
            <address>
               <name>Beyond 2022: Ireland's Virtual Record Treasury</name>
               <addrLine>Trinty College Dublin, the University of Dublin</addrLine>
               <addrLine>College Green</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Dublin 2</addrLine>
               <addrLine>D02 PN40</addrLine>
               <country>Ireland</country>
            </address>
         </publicationStmt>
         <!-- Part of a series? -->
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Pipe rolls (The National Archives, E 372).</title>
            <idno>E 372</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <!-- Details about the manuscript. -->
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <repository>The National Archives</repository>
                  <idno>E 372/150</idno>
                  <idno type="b2022-idno">UK-KeNA E 372/150</idno>
                  <idno type="URI"
                     >https://discovery.nationalarchives.gov.uk/details/r/C4050642</idno>
                  <msName>Pipe roll, 1304 Michaelmas – 1305 Michaelmas.</msName>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>A parchment roll.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <!-- Details about the encoding -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <!-- Project description-->
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created as part of the Medieval Gold Seam of the 'Beyond 2022: Ireland's Virtual
               Record Treasury' Research Project, Phase 2 (2019–22)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <!-- Editorial declaration -->
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>The guiding principle is to make this edition of the accounts of the medieval Irish
               Exchequer (and other medieval records populating Beyond 2022 Virtual Record Treasury)
               as intelligible as possible to as wide an audience as possible. To that end, due to
               their generally brief, formulaic nature the records are more or less directly
               translated into modern English without losing the literal, technical sense of the
               original language, which is almost exclusively Latin.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <!-- Non bibliographic aspects of the text -->
      <profileDesc>
         <!-- Languages used in the encoding. -->
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <!-- Details about the creation of the text. -->
         <creation>
            <date from="1301-09-30" to="1302-09-29">30 September 1301 to 29 September 1302</date>
         </creation>
         <!-- Beyond 2022 knowledge graph. For people, places and organizations/offices -->
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://ont.beyond2022.ie/ontology#">
               <term ref="https://kb.beyond2022.ie/person/615_-_0000_g>">Edward I</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <!-- searchFast: https://fast.oclc.org/searchfast/ -->
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="https://fast.oclc.org/">
               <term ref="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/1205427.rdf.xml">Ireland</term>
               <term ref="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/1020301.rdf.xml">Middle Ages</term>
               <term ref="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/924349.rdf.xml">Finance</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <!-- Changes made to the document -->
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change status="draft" when="2020-11-06" resp="#elizabeth-biggs">Initial draft</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <div>

            <pb type="rotulus" n="40"/>
            <pb type="membrane" n="1"/>

            <p>Account of Richard de Bereford, treasurer of Ireland, of his receipts from the
               treasury of Ireland from <date type="regnal" when="1300-06-08">8 June 28 Edward
                  I</date> when he was granted the office of treasurer and from <date type="regnal"
                  when="1300-07-06">6 July <supplied>1300</supplied> 28 Edward I</date> when he
               arrived in Dublin until 33 Edward I. These expenses have been authenticated by the
               counter rolls of Henry de Walton, Gilbert de Arderne, Robert de Whatton and John de
               Donnore, successively chamberlains of the exchequer in Ireland for the same time.</p>

            <div>
               <opener>Receipts for the last part of 28 <supplied>Edward I</supplied></opener>

               <ab>The same R accounts for <measure type="currency">£162 9s 1d</measure> of the
                  farms returned and others received at the Dublin exchequer from the aforesaid
                  translation of St Thomas the Martyr 28 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> to Michaelmas
                  next following, as is contained in a roll of particulars of the upper receipt
                  which the same Richard paid in the treasury, and in the aforesaid counter-roll of
                  the aforesaid Henry de Walton, the chamberlain, for the aforesaid time.</ab>
               <ab>And for <measure type="currency">£20</measure> received from merchants of the
                  society of the Ricciardi <note><foreign xml:lang="lat"
                        >Ric<ex>er</ex>or<ex>um</ex></foreign></note> of Lucca of his debts in
                  England, viz. in part payment of debts in which the same merchants hold of the
                  king, during the aforesaid time as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">46s 8 <supplied>d</supplied>d</measure> received
                  from seizing wine <note><foreign xml:lang="lat">p<ex>ri</ex>sa
                     vinorum</foreign></note> during the aforesaid time as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£8 13s</measure> received from the <add
                     place="above">issues</add> of the church benefices of Nicholas de Clere, once
                  treasurer of Ireland in various bishoprics of Ireland in part payment of the
                  arrears of his account for the time in which he was treasurer of Ireland as is
                  contained in a roll of particulars received of the goods of the said Nicholas
                  which were paid in the treasury, and in the counter-roll of the said Henry of the
                  same goods.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£9 16s 8d</measure> received of arrears of the
                  fifteenth, once granted to the king in Ireland for the same time as is contained
                  in a roll of particulars of the same fifteenth which were paid in the treasury and
                  the counter roll of the aforesaid Henry of the same fifteenth.</ab>
            </div>

            <div>
               <opener><date from="1300-11-20" to="1301-11-19" type="regnal">29 <supplied>Edward
                        I</supplied></date></opener>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£3659 10s 11d</measure> of the customs, farms,
                  receipts, debts and other payments received at the same Dublin exchequer from the
                  aforesaid Michaelmas 28 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, the beginning of 29
                     <supplied>Edward I</supplied> until the same day in the following year
                        <note><foreign xml:lang="lat">anno revolutio</foreign></note>, viz. for
                  Michaelmas term 28 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, Hilary, Easter and Trinity terms
                  29 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, just as is contained in a roll of particulars of
                  the great receipt <note><foreign xml:lang="lat">magne recepte</foreign></note> for
                  the whole year 29 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> of the things which were paid in
                  the treasury and in a counter roll of the said Henry for the same time.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£475 22d</measure> received during the same time
                  from the merchants of the society of the Ricciardi of Lucca in part payment of the
                  debts, which they hold of the king as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£234 2s 3½d</measure> received at the same time
                  from the new customs on wool, leather and wool-fells in Ireland as is contained
                  there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£200</measure> for the same time of the issues of
                  the Dublin exchange by Tholosanus Donati as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">1 mark</measure> received during the same time of
                  weighed gold, 16d found and sold as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£8</measure> received during the same time from
                  the profits of buying base coins <note><foreign xml:lang="lat"
                        >pollardorum</foreign></note> and plate as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of £<measure type="currency">643 19s</measure> received during the same time
                  from the aid granted to the king in Ireland as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£15</measure> received during the same time from
                  the issues held by Geoffrey de Lisniaco, the German, and of the power held from
                  the lord king of France, in the hands of the king on account of the war between
                  the king and the king of France, as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">100s</measure> received from John de Ponte in
                  part payment of <measure type="currency">£52</measure> in which he is held by the
                  king for wine formerly received at Leeds <note>Ledes</note> by a royal writ from
                  the English exchequer directed to the said Dublin exchequer, as is contained
                  there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">1 mar</measure> received from the goods of the
                  foreign merchants in the power of the king of France, as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£117 1d</measure> received for the aforesaid year
                  29 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> of the ecclesiastical goods of Nicholas de Clere,
                  once treasurer of Ireland in various bishoprics in Ireland in part payment of the
                  arrears of his account when he was treasurer in Ireland as is contained in a roll
                  of the same Nicholas’ goods received in the said year 29 <supplied>Edward
                     I</supplied> and various years after, which were paid in the treasury and in
                  the counter roll of Henry of the aforesaid goods during the same time.</ab>
               <ab>And <measure type="currency">£53 14s 1½d</measure> received during the aforesaid
                  time of the arrears of the fifteenth granted to the king as in contained in the
                  roll of particulars of the said fifteenth of the said year 29 <supplied>Edward
                     I</supplied> and other various years following which the said Richard paid in
                  the treasury and in the counter roll of the said Henry of the aforesaid
                  fifteenth.</ab>
               <ab>And in <measure type="currency">£4 18s 9½d</measure> received in the said year 29
                     <supplied>Edward I</supplied> of the arrears of the service of Cumbre in the
                  time when J. Wogan was justiciar as is contained in a roll of the arrears of the
                  same service of the said year 29 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and various years
                  following and in the counter-roll of the said Henry of the aforesaid service.</ab>
            </div>
            <div>
               <opener>30 <supplied>Edward I</supplied></opener>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£4326 2s 1d</measure> of the customs, farms,
                  receipts, debts and other payments received at the same Dublin exchequer from the
                  aforesaid Michaelmas 29 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, beginning 30
                     <supplied>Edward I</supplied> until the same day in the following year, viz.
                  Michaelmas term 29 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and Hilary, Easter and Trinity
                  terms 30 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> just as is contained in a roll of
                  particulars of the great receipt, which were paid in the treasury and in the
                  counter-roll of the said Henry for the same time.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£705 8s 1½d</measure> received during the same
                  time of aids granted to the king as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£530 16s 8½d</measure> received during the same
                  time from the new customs of wool, leather and sheep-fells in Ireland as is
                  contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£13 6s 8d</measure> received from Geoffrey de
                  Genevile, of what he had borrowed from? the king’s Wardrobe, as is contained
                  there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£7 8s</measure> received of the issues of the
                  lands of Geoffrey de Lisignago <note>Lisniato</note>, the German, of the power
                     <note>potestate</note> of the king of France in the hands of the king due to
                  the war between the king and the king of France, as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">26s 8d</measure> received of the goods of the
                  foreign merchants of the power of the king of France as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£26 16 s 9½d</measure> received in the return of
                  provisions sent to Scotland, as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">60s</measure> received during the same period of
                  the profit from the purchase of debased coins, as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£22</measure> received from seizing wine during
                  the same time as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£520</measure> received during the same time of
                  the issues of the Dublin exchange by Tholosam Donati as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£90 7s 2d</measure> received during the same year
                  30 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> of the church goods of Nicholas de Clere, once
                  treasurer of Ireland in various bishoprics in Ireland in part satisfaction of the
                  arrears of his account, from the time when he was treasurer in Ireland as is
                  contained in a roll of the goods of the same Nicholas received in various years
                  which were paid in the treasury and in the counter-roll of the said Henry
                  concerning the aforesaid goods.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£39 13 ¼d</measure> received during the aforesaid
                  year 30 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> of the arrears of the fifteenth granted in
                  Ireland as is contained in a roll of particulars of the arrears of the fifteenth
                  in various years, which the said Richard paid in the treasury and in the
                  counter-roll of the said Henry of the aforesaid fifteenth.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">47s 9d</measure> received in Trinity term 30
                     <supplied>Edward I</supplied> of the arrears of the service of Cumbre in the
                  time when John Wogan was justiciar of Ireland as is contained in a roll of the
                  same service in various years and in the counter-roll of the said Henry.</ab>
            </div>
            <div>
               <opener>31 <supplied>Edward I</supplied></opener>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£4619 3s 4d</measure> of customs, farms,
                  payments, debts and other payments received at the same Dublin exchequer from the
                  aforesaid Michaelmas 30 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, beginning 31
                     <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, until the same day in the following year, viz.
                  for Michaelmas term 30 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, and Hilary, Easter and
                  Trinity terms 31 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> as is contained in a roll of
                  particulars of the great receipt <note>magne recepte</note> which were paid in the
                  treasury and in a counter-roll of the said Henry of the same receipts for the same
                  time.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£164</measure> received during the same time of
                  the aid granted to the king in Ireland as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£248 3s</measure> received during the same time
                  from the merchants of the society of the Ricciardi of Lucca in part payment of the
                  debts which they hold of the king as contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£8 8s 1½d</measure> received during the same time
                  of the the issues of the Dublin exchange by Tholosam? Donati as is contained
                  there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£7 6s 8d</measure> received from the return of
                  provisions sent to Scotland as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£229 1d</measure> received during the aforesaid
                  time of the ecclesiastical goods of Nicholas de Clere, once treasurer, in various
                  bishoprics in Ireland in part payment of the arrears of his account in the time
                  when he was treasurer in Ireland as is contained in a roll of the goods of the
                  same Nicholas received in various years which were paid in the treasury and in a
                  counter-roll of the said Henry of the aforesaid goods.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£79 14s 8d</measure> received during the
                  aforesaid time of the arrears of the fifteenth granted to the king in Ireland as
                  is contained in a roll of particulars of the arrears of the said fifteenth during
                  various years which the said Richard paid in the treasury and in the counter-roll
                  of the said Henry of the aforesaid fifteenth.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">100s</measure> received of the arrears of various
                  services as is contained in a roll of arrears of the same services in various
                  years, which the same Richard paid in the treasury and in a counter-roll of the
                  said Henry of the aforesaid services.</ab>
            </div>

            <div>
               <opener>32 <supplied>Edward I</supplied></opener>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£3,475 15s ¼d</measure> of customs, farms,
                  payments, debts and other payments received at the said Dublin exchequer from the
                  aforesaid Michaelmas ending 31 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and beginning 32
                     <supplied>Edward I</supplied> until the same day in the following year, viz for
                  Michaelmas term at the end of 31 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and Hilary, Easter
                  and Trinity terms 32 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> as is contained in a roll of
                  particulars of the great receipts paid in the treasury and in a counter-roll of
                  the aforesaid Henry of the same receipts for the same time.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£187 14s 1¾d</measure> received of the return of
                  provisions sent by the king to Scotland as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£98 13s 6d</measure> received during the same
                  time of the aid granted to the king as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£11 13s 4d</measure> received during the same
                  time of the new customs on wool, leather, and wool-fells as is contained
                  there.</ab>
               <ab>And <measure type="currency">106s 8d</measure> received from John de Ponte in
                  part payment of the <measure type="currency">£52</measure> in which the king holds
                  for the wine which was formerly received at Leeds <note>Ledes</note> by a writ of
                  the king of the exchequer in England directing the said Dublin exchequer as is
                  contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And <measure type="currency">£192 13s 4d</measure> received during the same time
                  from the merchants of the society of Ricciardi of Lucca in part payment of the
                  debts which the same merchants hold of the king as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£13 9s 10 ½d</measure> received from seizing wine
                  during the same time as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">100s</measure> received of the goods of foreign
                  merchants of the power of the king of France as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£88 2s 1d</measure> received during the aforesaid
                  time of the ecclesiastical goods of Nicholas de Clere, once treasurer of Ireland
                  in various bishoprics in Ireland in part payment of the arrears of his account
                  from the time when he was treasurer in Ireland, as is contained in a roll of the
                  goods of the same Nicholas received in various years which were paid in the
                  treasury and in a counter-roll of the said Henry of the aforesaid goods.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£68 16s 2¼d</measure> received during the same
                  time of the arrears of the fifteenth granted to the king as is contained in a roll
                  of particulars of the arrears of the fifteenth in various years which the same
                  Richard paid in the treasury and in a counter-roll of the said Henry of the same
                  fifteenth.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£17 10s</measure> received during the same time
                  of various services in Ireland as are contained in a roll of particulars of the
                  arrears of the same services paid by the said Richard in the treasury and in a
                  counter-roll of the said Henry of the receipt of the same services.</ab>
            </div>

            <div>
               <opener>First half of 33 <supplied>Edward I</supplied></opener>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£1962 11s 11¾d</measure> received from customs,
                  farms, receipts, debts and other payments at the same Dublin exchequer from the
                  aforesaid Michaelmas ending 32 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and beginning 33
                     <supplied>Edward I</supplied> until Easter next following, viz for Michaelmas
                  term 32 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, Hilary term 33 <supplied>Edward
                     I</supplied>, viz for the first half of the year 33 <supplied>Edward
                     I</supplied> as is contained in a roll of particulars of the great receipts
                  which were paid in the treasury and in a counter-roll of the said Henry of the
                  said receipts of the same time.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">26s 8d</measure> received from John de Ponte in
                  part payment of <measure type="currency">£52</measure> which he holds of the king
                  for wine formerly received in Leeds by a writ of the king in the exchequer of
                  England directed to the said Dublin exchequer as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£355 4s 6d</measure> received during the same
                  period from the society of the Ricciardi of Lucca in part payment of the debts
                  which they hold of the king as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£77 6s 8d</measure> received from the seizing of
                  wine during the same time as is contained there.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£64 17s 11½d</measure> received during the same
                  time of the ecclesiastical goods of Nicholas de Clere, once treasurer of Ireland
                  in various bishoprics of Ireland in part payment of the arrears of his account
                  from the time when he was treasurer in Ireland as is contained in a roll of the
                  goods of the same Nicholas received in various years which were paid in the
                  treasury and in a counter-roll of the said Henry of the aforesaid goods.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£54 12s 4 ¼d</measure> received during the
                  aforesaid time of the arrears of the fifteenth granted to the king as is contained
                  in a roll of particulars of the arrears of the said fifteenth in various years
                  which the same Richard paid in the treasury and in a counter-roll of the said
                  Henry of the aforesaid fifteenth.</ab>
               <ab>And of <measure type="currency">£613s 4d</measure> received from the arrears of
                  various services as are contained in a roll of particulars of the arrears of the
                  service of the new castle of Makynegan in the time when Brother W de Ros, prior of
                  St John of Jerusalem in Ireland was deputy to John Wogan, justiciar of Ireland as
                  is contained in a roll of particulars which the said Richard paid in the treasury
                  and in a counter-roll of the said Henry of the aforesaid service.</ab>
               <ab>Totals of the receipts of the treasurer in Ireland from the last part of 28
                  [Edward 1], 29 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> 30 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, 31
                     <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, 32 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and the first
                  half of 33 <supplied>Edward I</supplied></ab>

               <closer>£24,499 17s 7½d</closer>
            </div>
            <div>
               <div>
                  <ab>In the treasury <measure type="currency">£11,267 4s 5d</measure></ab>
                  <ab>Item in the treasury <measure type="currency">£60</measure> of the marriage of
                     Margaret de Staunton of which charges <note>illeg. due to fold</note> term 30
                        <supplied>Edward I</supplied></ab>
                  <ab>Item in the treasury <measure type="currency">£55 2 marks</measure> by John
                     Wogan for the same Richard de Bereford of the issues of Ireland</ab>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <ab>Issues and Expenses</ab>

                  <ab>Richard de Bereford for his annual fee £40 from 8 July 28 Edward I until
                     Michaelmas next following and from the same Michaelmas to Easter 33
                        <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, that is the last quarter of 28
                        <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and for the years 29, 30, 31, 32
                        <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and the first half of 32 <note>sic. should be
                        33</note> £190</ab>
               </div>
            </div>


         </div>
         <pb type="mebrane" n="2"/>
         <div>
            <ab>And to Master Adam de Botindon, chancellor of the Dublin exchequer, receiving £10
               yearly by the same ordinance and in the same manner of his fees in 29 and 30 [Edward
               I] <measure type="currency">£20</measure> and the same Adam died on the third day
               after Michaelmas <note><foreign xml:lang="lat">an’ festum sci’
                  michis’</foreign></note> in the said 30 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and from the
               death of the same Adam the aforesaid office of chancellor was vacant until Hilary 31
                  <supplied>Edward I</supplied> at which time the king granted to Gilbert de Ardern
               the aforesaid office of chancellor as is contained there.</ab>
            <ab>And to the aforesaid Gilbert de Ardern, chancellor of the said Dublin exchequer for
               his customary fee £10 annually by the same ordinance from the aforesaid Hilary 31
                  <supplied>Edward I</supplied> until Easter 33 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, that
               is from the last three quarters of 31 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, 32
                  <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, and the first half of 33 <supplied>Edward
                  I</supplied>, £22 10s as is contained there.</ab>
            <ab>And to Richard de Saham and William de Meones, the two barons of the said Dublin
               exchequer each of whom received yearly 20 marks for their fee by the same ordinance
               for 29, 30, 31, 32 and the first half of 32 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> £120 as is
               contained there.</ab>
            <ab>And for the two scribes writing the great rolls of the king in the said Dublin
               exchequer from Sunday next after the octave of Trinity, that is from 30 June 28
                  <supplied>Edward I</supplied> to 6 August next following when the said Dublin
               exchequer was open, and also for various days in which the same exchequer similarly
               was open in 29, 30, 31 and 32 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and for the first half of
               33 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> £46 19s 2d as is contained in a roll of payments and
               expenses of various years which were paid in the treasury and in a counter-roll of
               the said Henry for the same time, viz that 5d to each of these scribes daily when the
               exchequer was open, as appears in the aforesaid ordinance.</ab>
            <ab>And to the same scribes for their robes for 28, 29, 30, 31 and 31 <supplied>Edward
                  I</supplied> £10, to each yearly 20s by the same ordinance, that is each year at
               Michaelmas as is contained there.</ab>
            <ab>And one of the remembrancers of the said Dublin exchequer for Trinity 28
                  <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and 29, 30, 31, 32, and for the first half of 33
                  <supplied>Edward I</supplied> £23 15s as is contained there, 100s yearly by the
               same ordinance.</ab>
            <ab>And the same remembrancer for his robes for the said years, 29, 30, 31, 32 and for
               the whole year in 33 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> 5 marks, that is 1 mark yearly as
               in the aforesaid ordinances, which mark he received once a year at Hilary according
               to custom as the same Richard said and the said Henry, the chamberlain,
               testified.</ab>
            <ab>And to the two clerks writing summonses <note><foreign xml:lang="lat"
                  >sum’</foreign></note>, for which they take yearly 2 marks according to the same
               ordinance at Trinity 28 and 29, 30, 31, 32 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and for the
               first half of 33 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, £12 <supplied>and</supplied> 1 mark
               as is contained there.</ab>
            <ab>And for the two chamberlains of the king there for their fees for 29, 30, 31, 32
                  <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and for the first half of 33 <supplied>Edward
                  I</supplied> £60, for which 10 marks yearly by the same ordinance, as is contained
               there.</ab>
            <ab>And for one of the aforesaid treasurer’s clerks in the king’s receipt in the said
               Dublin exchequer for various days, on which the said exchequer was open, from the
               aforesaid 13 June 28 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> to Michaelmas next following and
               in 29, 30, 31, 32 and the first half of 33 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> £23 9s 1d,
               5d daily at the open exchequer by the same ordinance as is contained there.</ab>
            <ab>And one of the doorkeepers <note><foreign xml:lang="lat">hostiarum</foreign>, sic.
                     <foreign xml:lang="lat">ostiarum</foreign></note> on each side of the exchequer
               for Trinity 28 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and 29, 30, 31, 32 and the first half of
               33 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> £4 15s, receiving yearly 20s as is contained
               there.</ab>
            <ab>And for the two chaplains celebrating divine <note>office</note>, one in the chapel
               of Dublin Castle and the other in the chapel of the Dublin exchequer for the final
               quarter 28 <supplied>Edward I</supplied>, 29, 30, 31 and 32 <supplied>Edward
                  I</supplied> and the first half of 33 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> £24 14s, each
               for their yearly stipends of 50s yearly and for wax 2s as is allocated for the same
               chaplains in the account of the said William de Essendon, treasurer of Ireland in the
               said account for 28 <supplied>Edward I</supplied> and 27 <supplied>Edward
                  I</supplied> and as is contained in the roll of particular payments and expenses
               of various years, which the same Richard received in the treasury and in the
               counter-roll of the said Henry, chamberlain, for the aforesaid time.</ab>
            <ab>And for 6 ells <note><foreign xml:lang="lat">ulnis</foreign></note> of cloth
                     <note><foreign xml:lang="lat">panni</foreign></note> bought to cover
                     <note><foreign xml:lang="lat">coop<ex>er</ex>iend’</foreign></note> the great
               exchequer and the exchequer of receipt at Dublin and for wax for sealing accounts and
               royal writs and for carrying the same accounts and writs to various counties and
               places, canvas <note><foreign xml:lang="lat">canauat’</foreign></note> for bags and
               sacks, pouches, parchment, ink, litter, coffers and locks, and other various and
               small things bought and repaired during the same time, <measure type="currency"
                  >£4618s 4d</measure> as is contained there.</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
